Register of the Daniel B. Luten Jr. Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Daniel B. Luten Jr. Papers
1931-1964
80064
Luten, Daniel B., 1908-
6 manuscript boxes (2.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
American demographer and technical adviser to the chief, Natural Resources Section, General Headquarters, Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers, Japan, 1948-1950. Materials include writings, correspondence, memoranda, statistics, clippings, and other printed matter, relating to natural resources and population in Japan, and the question of birth control.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research. Access to audiovisual materials requires at least two weeks advance notice. Audiovisual materials include sound recordings, video recordings, and motion picture film. Hoover staff will determine whether use copies of the materials requested can be made available. Some materials may not be accessible even with advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives Audiovisual Specialist for further information.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1980
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1908, March 15 Born, Indianapolis, Indiana
1929 B.A. Darthmouth College
1933 Ph.D. Chemistry, University of California, Berkeley
1935-1961 Research Chemist, Development Supervisor, Shell Oil Company adn Shell Development Company, Martinez and Emeryville, California
1948-1950 (on leave) Technical Advisor to the Chief, Natural Resources Section, General Headquarters, Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers, Japan
1962-1975 Lecturer, University of California Berkeley
Scope and Content of Collection
American demographer and technical adviser to the chief, Natural Resources Section, General Headquarters, Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers, Japan, 1948-1950. Materials include writings, correspondence, memoranda, statistics, clippings, and other printed matter, relating to natural resources and population in Japan, and the question of birth control.
Arrangement
Arranged into four series: Correspondence, Subject File, Press Comments of demographic, economic and political problems of Japan, and Press comments of demographic, economic and political problems of the countries other than Japan.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers.; Birth control--Japan.; Military government.; Natural resources--Japan.; Japan--History--Allied occupation, 1945-1952.; Japan--Population.
Container List
- Correspondence, 1948-1950
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondant.
  - Miscellaneous, 1948-1950; 21 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ackerman, Adward A., 1949-1950; 16 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Civil Librerties Union, 1950; 2 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Blewett, W. V., 1948; 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Evans, Roger, F., 1948; 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Kato, Shidzue I., 1949; 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Manazuru, Kanagawa, 1949; 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Miyashita, K., 1950; 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers. General Headquarters. Statistics nad Reports Section., 1949; 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Thompson, Warren. S., 1949; 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Time magazine, 1948; 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Thoru, Ishimitsu, 1949; 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Unidentified, 1949; 2 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Whelption, P.K., 1949-1950; 2 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Subject File, 1939-1964
  Bibliography, bradcase summaries, charts, letteres, maps, memoranda, minutes, notes, reports, research study, short story, speeches, synopsis of a movie. Arranged alphabeticaly by subject.
  - Health promotion in the Far East, Report, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Japan
    - Agriculture nad Food Supply. Memoranda, notes, reports, and statistics., 1946-1950 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Birth control. Broadcast summaries, interviews, letters, memoranda, minutes, notes, reports, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Communicatble diseases. Statistics, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Demographic Survey. Letters, memoranda, notes, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Demography, econcomy, resources
      - Miscellaneous. Bibliography, letter, map, notes, reports, short story, statistics, synopsis of a movie, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Ackerman, Edward. A. Letters, notes, reports, 1948-1951 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - "America's town meeting of the air" Broadcast from Edward Pyle theater, in Tokyo, 30-Aug-49 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Ellliston, Herbert. Letter, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Evans, Roger F. Letter, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Furukawa, Heroshi. Report, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Hoashi, Kei. Report, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Honda, Naofumi. Letter, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Japanese Government. Ecomnomic Stabilization Board. Report, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Japanese Government. Ministry of Education. Textbook, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Japanese Government. Ministry of Welfare. Reports, statistics, letter, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
      - Japanese Government. Prime Minister's office. Reports, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Luten, Daniel B., Jr. Memoranda, report, speech, 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Luten, Daniel B., Jr. notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - MacArthur, Douglas. Interview, letter, report, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Mainichi -- Population problems research council, reports, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Makagawa, Tomanaga. Report, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Notesten, F.W.; Taeuber, I.B.; Evans, R.F.; Balfour, M.C. Report, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Oshima, Tsurutaro. Letter, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Oversears Movement Society. Memorandum, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Shapeero, Lorraine. Research study, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Stone, Margaret. Letters, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers. General Headquarters. Demographic survey, letter, memoranda, statistics, 1946-1950 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers. General Headquarters. Natural Resources Section. Letters, memoranda, minutes, reports, 1948-1950 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Tachi, Minoru. Report, speech., 1949 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Thompson, Warren S. Bibliography, letters, memoranda, reports, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - United Nations. Soviet delagate's speech, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - U.S. Army. First Corps. Policy statement, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - USSR. Moscow Broadcast, 10-Jul-49 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Whelpton, P.K. Bibliography, letters, notes, reports, 1939-1950 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Energy and Forestry. Memoranda, reports, speeches, statistics, 1947-1950 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Government. Ministry of Welfare. Organization and structure. Imperial ordinances, 1938-1946 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Housing Problem. Construction project, statistics, report, 1948-1950 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - International Documents. Charter of the United Nations, documents pertaining to the surrentder of Japan, 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - International Educational and Cultural Associations. Layout of activities, statistsics, statutes, teaching methods, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - "Japanese Natural Resources" Book by Edward A. Ackerman. Problkem of Distribution. Letters, memoranda, notes, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Vital statistics, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Korea -- Bibliogrpahy in European languages, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Supreme Commanderfor the Allied Powers. General Headquarters. Structure and composition. Memoranda, notes, organization plan, statutes, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Union Internationale pour L'Etude Scientifique de Population. Tenative program of assemby at Geneva, 29 August-3 September 1949 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - World Population. Statistics, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Press Comments of demographic, economic and political problems of Japan, 1945-1950
  Clippings from magazines and newspapers, typed copies of magazine and newspaper articles, reviews of press. Arranged chronologically.
  - 1945-1947 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 1948 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - January - March 1949 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - April 1949 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - May 1949 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - June 1949 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - July - September 1949 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - October - November 1949 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - December 1949 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - January 1950 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - February - March 1950 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - April - July 1950 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Press Comments of demographic, economic and political problems of countries other than Japan, 1931-1950
  Clippings from magazines and newspapers, typed copies of magazine and newspaper articles, graphs. Arranged alphabetically by name of country.
  - General, 1931-1949 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Argentina, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Australia, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - China, 1949-1950 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Great Britain, 1948-1949 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Italy, 1948-1949 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Mexico, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Netherlands, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - USA, 1940-1949 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - USSR, 1948-1949 (Box 6, Folder 12)